<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apology for schoole-masters tending to the aduauncement of learning, and to the vertuous education of children. By Thomas Morrice, Master of Artes.</title>
            <author>Morrice, Thomas, fl. 1617-1619.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07793</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120701</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855895</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855895</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21403</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07793)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21403)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 996:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apology for schoole-masters tending to the aduauncement of learning, and to the vertuous education of children. By Thomas Morrice, Master of Artes.</title>
                  <author>Morrice, Thomas, fl. 1617-1619.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Bernard Alsop, for Richard Flemming, and are to be sold at his shoppe at the signe of the three Flower-de-Luces in Saint Pauls' Alley neere Saint Gregories Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: An apologie for schoolemasters.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D (-A1,2).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Teachers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21403:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21403:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGY FOR SCHOOLE-MASTERS,</p>
            <p>Tending to the aduauncement of Learning, and to the vertuous education of Children.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS MORRICE, <hi>Maſter of Artes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Bernard Alſop,</hi> for <hi>Richard Flemming,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shoppe at the Signe of the three <hi>Flower-de Luces</hi> in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Alley neere Saint <hi>Gregories</hi> Church. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21403:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21403:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Lord <hi>Roſſe,</hi> Sonne and Heyre apparent of the <hi>Right Honourable Earle</hi> of Rutland.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y eſpeciall good Lord, I preſume to preſet to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor this title trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe concerning learned Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and the Teacher thereof: Seeing that as God hath bleſſed you now in your Childhood with a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and moſt Noble diſpoſition, a louing and kinde nature, quicke ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, pregnant wit, ready vtt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and firme memory: ſo if it
<pb facs="tcp:21403:3"/>pleaſeth his Diuine Maieſtie (which I heartily deſire) to grant you proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous health, I hope by the carefull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation of your right Honourable Parents, you will in proceſſe of time attayne to excellent knowledge. Your vertuous, and right Honourable ſiſter the Lady <hi>Katherine,</hi> may obtayne the perfect vnderſtanding of the <hi>Latine</hi> tongue in very ſhort time, ſuch is the excellency of her wit and memory, if ſhe continue as ſhe began in the ſtudie thereof. Good endeauouers, euen the beſt enterpriſes, by ſiniſter ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whiſpered, or ſcandalous aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſcattered, are ſometimes hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. I truſt your Honour will accept of this ſlender token, offered with as good a will to your Lordſhip, as the widdow did her ſmall mite to the Treaſury; or the poore man his hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of cleere and cleane water to the <hi>Perſian</hi> King <hi>Artaxerſes.</hi> For albeiit
<pb facs="tcp:21403:3"/>my body, againſt my will, is abſent from you, notwithſtanding my minde is with you, my memory of you, my loue towards you, and my prayers to Almightie God are for your health, long life, and perpetuall happineſſe. So I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours euer deuoted. Thomas Morrice.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21403:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21403:4"/>
            <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing that (gentle Reader) all men are naturally deſirous of knowledge: and that many haue bin aduaunced thereby, to Nobilitie, Principality, Regall and Imperiall authoritie. And conſidering that this knowledge, whether it be <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſcentia,</hi> as the <hi>Platoniſtes,</hi> or <hi>de nouo,</hi> as the <hi>Peripatetikes</hi> doe more truely maintaine: is inſtilled, and deriued vnto vs originally, &amp; ordinarily by Schoole-maſters,
<pb facs="tcp:21403:5"/>which are the inſtrumentall cauſes thereof, ordayned by Almighty God to that intent and purpoſe.</p>
            <p>I thought it not amiſſe, in this ſhort treatiſe, to incite and ſtirre vp ſome, which in this age are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant herein, to a due conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to a more religious reſpect, to a more requiſite vſage, and to a more gratefull remembrance of Schoolemaſters. Albeit there be faults in all profeſſions, and in all fortes of people; yet ſome imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections wee ought rather with <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Iaphet</hi> to couer, then with curſed <hi>Cham</hi> to ſcoffe at. The ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt roſe hath a prickle; and the fineſt cloth a bracke. I requeſt thee to be aduertiſed, that I treate here of learned and honeſt Schoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, not of vnlearned and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt intruders into that function.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abel</hi> will offer ſacrifice, <hi>Cain</hi> will
<pb facs="tcp:21403:5"/>ſacrifice too: <hi>Iacob</hi> will haue a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>Eſau</hi> would haue a bleſſing: too: <hi>Simon Petter</hi> will worke mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> wold do ſo too: <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great wil be a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, <hi>Thraſo</hi> will be one to: <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian</hi> will be a Schoolemaſter, <hi>Rom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> will be one too. The impes of Sathan, ſometimes wil be the apes of the Children of God. I doe not defend irregular, vnlearned, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit perſons, which intrude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and vſurpe the office of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: but approued, learned, &amp; diſcreete Schoolemaſters: which for the benefit of publique-weales are not a little to be regarded. Thus wiſhing thee increaſe of vertuous knowledge, I reſt euer thy Well-willer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T.M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:21403:6"/>
            <head>¶ The Contents of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe following.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> The dignitie of Learning and the degrees thereof maintayned.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The election of a Schoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and the education of Noble and generous Children briefly declared.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> The Office of a Schoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, and his place, being entertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a Noblemans houſe, diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> The errors of them which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon, or at leaſt debaſe learning and the Profeſſors thereof, diſplayed and confuted.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> The confutation of them which hold, that a Schoolemaſter is a ſeruant
<pb facs="tcp:21403:6"/>to any ſubiect, who in conſideration of learning giueth him allowance.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> A demonſtration how neceſſary Schoolemaſters are for the good of publike Weales, and how they ought to be regarded.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> A <hi>Frenchman</hi> is not ſo fit to teach children in England, to read, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, ſpeake and write <hi>Engliſh, Latine,</hi> and <hi>Greeke,</hi> as an <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> The abſurd opinion of them which preferre the <hi>French</hi> tongue before the <hi>Latine,</hi> or doe paralell it with the <hi>Latine</hi> tongue, impugned.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> The vſe and benefite of trauell, after the knowledge tongue is attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21403:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21403:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN</hi> APOLOGY <hi>for Schoole-maſters, tending to</hi> the aduauncement of Learning, and to the vertuous education <hi>of Children.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am determined (GOD aſſiſting me) to make an Apology againſt proud and blind ignorance; the only aduerſary to noble and learned knowledge: for, <hi>Scientia non habet inimicum praeter ignorantem;</hi> Knowledge hath no enemy but the ignorant perſon,
<pb facs="tcp:21403:8"/>who reputeth the Schoolemaſter, and teacher of the Liberall Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: albeit he be a Doctor, or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Arts, to be a ſeruant to any ſubiect in Chriſtendome. I ſay, to any ſubiect: for I confeſſe, that he is a ſeruant to God, and to his King. Wherin I purpoſe to proue, that by the Diuine Law, by the Law of Nature, and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by the Conſtitutions and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons Eccleſiaſtical: by the Statute Law of our Realme, by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Heathen men, illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by naturall reaſon, that a Schoolemaſter, as a Schoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and teacher of the Liberall Sciences, is not a ſeruant to any ſubiect, much leſſe an inferiour ſeruant. He doth acknowledge in all humilitie his Lord, of whom he receiueth his allowance, to bee his eſpeciall good Lord, his very
<pb facs="tcp:21403:8"/>Honourable benefactor, his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Mecenas</hi> or Patrone, to whom he belongeth, of whom he depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and to whom in all liberall duetie he is oblieged.</p>
            <p>Schoolemaſters, who haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken degrees of Schoole in the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſities of this Land, leſt they doe otherwiſe, let them remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their Oath: for they haue ſworne to defend and maintaine their degrees. They muſt not make the Profeſſion of the Liberall Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſeruile, being Maſters of Arts, by reaſon of the teaching thereof, they ought not to be inferiour ſeruants. All learned men, ancient and moderne, might iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee thought vnprouident, and vnwiſe, for beſtowing ſo long time, ſo much paines, ſo great charges to attaine to Learning, and the degrees thereof, if by tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb facs="tcp:21403:9"/>of it to other ſubiects, they themſelues ſhould become inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſeruants.</p>
            <p>The moſt Noble Earles of this Kingdome doe take the degree of Maſter of Arts willingly, as an Ornament to their Nobilitie, which they would not doe, if they held the degree ſeruile, or the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſeruants, in reſpect of their Profeſſion of the Arts. I requeſt not to be miſtaken, for I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and confeſſe, that Maſters of Arts may very well, and not without cauſe, bee Noble-mens ſeruants, in offices, and places ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to ſeruants; but not as their Chapleines, or their Schoolemaſters; for herein they exerciſe their Profeſſions of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and of Arts, which are not ſeruile, and this they muſt defend, as they are bound by Oath, and I
<pb facs="tcp:21403:9"/>hope they will not make ſhipwreck of their conſciences. Euery one is to be regarded, and eſteemed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his vocation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and the ſubiect or obiect thereof about the which he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant: The Diuine for his <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.</hi> The Lawyer for adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and execution of Iuſtice. The Phiſician for the preſeruation of the health of the body. The Schoolemaſter for the good edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of children. The Steward for the ouerſeeing and well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of ſeruants, who are inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to the children.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, ſeeing that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is the reward of vertuous Learning, and Learning the promotor, or aduauncer, the maintayner, and principall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of Nobilitie, it ſeemeth to bee great want of diſcretion,
<pb facs="tcp:21403:10"/>to make a Schoolemaſter an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ſeruant: for how will the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ingenious children be ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated to learning, whereby they may become worthy Gouernours of their Countrey, when they ſhall perceiue the teacher thereof to be reputed an inferiour ſeruant, and his learning ſeruile. This will be diſtaſtfull, and a diſcouragement to their Honourable natures and diſpoſitions, and a whetſtone to pride and diſobedience, the very bane of youth. For Noblemen, and Gentlemens children are to bee brought vp in humilitie, the roote of all vertues. Otherwiſe, by ſiniſter mindes, and meanes, not onely the Liberall Sciences, and the Profeſſors thereof are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced; but alſo the children are by their owne Parents diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and debaſed, by making an
<pb facs="tcp:21403:10"/>imputed ſeruant their Maſter, to the exceeding hurt &amp; hinderance of their good education and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite in knowledge, the aduauncer and preſeruer of true Nobilitie, whereby, in proceſſe of time, they may become wiſe Councellours, fit and diſcreete Gouernours; For how will the Noble and generous children ſtand in obedience, due awe, and regard to a ſeruant? or loue and delight in learning ſo vilifyed? This prepoſterous courſe, by all probabilitie, will breede in them contempt of the one, and diſlike of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>There is an obiection propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the proud ignorant to bee confuted; who euer (ſay they) receiueth meate, drinke, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, for the execution of bis Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, or function, is a ſeruant
<pb facs="tcp:21403:11"/>vnto him, of whom hee receiueth it.</p>
            <p>I anſwere, that this aſſertion in the generall is manifeſtly falſe and erronious. Offices and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are not to bee huddled vp, and confounded, but to be iudicially diſtinguiſhed. There are ſome Offices ſeruile, they who execute theſe, are ſeruants. There are other Offices liberall, they who vndertake theſe, are not ſeruants, but onely to GOD, and their King; albeit they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue allowance, ſtipend, ſee, or ſalary, as their deſerts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. Such are the Profeſſours of Diuinitie, Lawe, Phiſicke, and the Liberall Sciences. Hee who holdeth theſe Sciences to be ſeruile, may bee yoked with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naxagoras,</hi> who held the Snow to be blacke. His opinion is erronius:
<pb facs="tcp:21403:11"/>And if hee perſiſt ſtiffe-necked therein, heretical, and worſe then Heatheniſh: for the Heathen men were not ſo depriued of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. A man giueth meate, drinke and money to a Lawyer for the deuiſing of lands, by making conueyances or aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances thereof to his ſonnes: Is the Lawyer therefore his ſeruant? Or in like manner, giueth to a Phyſitian for miniſtring Phyſicke to his children: Is the Phyſitian therefore his ſeruant? One giueth yearely certaine quarters of wheat, and malte, which are equiualent to meate, and drinke, and money, to an other, becauſe hee beſtoweth vpon his ſonne, for terme of life a Tenement: Is he therefore who beſtoweth the Tenement the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſeruant? Likewiſe one gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth meate, drinke and money to
<pb facs="tcp:21403:12"/>a Schoolemaſter, becauſe hee conferreth vpon his ſonne Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which by the iudgement of the Wiſe is betttet then a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement Is the Schoolemaſter therefore his ſeruant? They who perſwade themſelues theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences to be true, are infected with an errour which is ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and preiudiciall to all Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities, Innes of the Court, and degrees of Learning, which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily haue aduanced, doe ſtill, and will aduance many diſcended of meane parentage, to true Gentry, true Nobility, and to high digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>After a Noble man his ſonne is ſixe yeares of age, diligent indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry is to bee vſed, and eſpeciall care is to bee taken, to haue a fitte and ſufficient Schoole-maſter for him. By the iudgement of the
<pb facs="tcp:21403:12"/>wiſe hee is deemed to be fitte, and ſufficient, who is adorned with theſe qualities, viz: Who is a man of a found belieefe, honeſt life, and ciuill conuerſation, an auncient man, rather then a young: For a young is commonly more proner to lewde luſt, more apt to giue badde example to his Scholler, more inconſiderate, of leſſe diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and experience, then an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient man. A man tryed for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodicall teaching, and trayning vp of children, and well allowed for the ſame: A man knowne to be learned, of ready vtterance, and perfect pronuntiation of ſpeech, and of reputation, hauing taken the degrees of learning. It may bee demaunded, why ſo lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a Maſter is to be prouided for a childe of ſuch tender yeares: I anſwere, that it is very requiſite, and needfull for diuers conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:21403:13"/>A veſſel being well ſeaſoned at the firſt, retayneth the taſte, and preſerueth the liquor, that ſhall bee powred thereinto. A ſure and firme foundation is firſt to be laid of pure and perfect Engliſh, to bee deliuered with decent action and geſture, with a right accent, and diſtinct pronuntiation: that when hee commeth to ripe yeares, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in eminent places, hee may communicate his learned know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge iudicially, and eloquently in his Natiue tongue, to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of his owne Country. In like manner, he is to bee taught pure and perfect Latine, &amp; if it be not too tedious for him, the Greeke may very well bee ioyned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, that he may not only reade with vnderſtanding for encreaſe of knowledge, moſt learned books in the ſaid languages, &amp; heare with
<pb facs="tcp:21403:13"/>iudgement exerciſes &amp; diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, accompliſhed by the learned of famous Vniuerſities; but alſo impart his intellectuall conceipts in eloquent Latine to forraine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, moſt honorably in any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant imploiment for the weale publike. An other conſideration isl, that a well learned Schoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is expedient, or rather neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, becauſe hee is to ſtay with his Schollers; for change of Maſters maketh ſeldome good Schollers: many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, many minds, many ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, many maners &amp; methods of teaching, which hurt &amp; hinder knowledge. The rowling ſtone ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth little moſſe. This noble child is to be kept in awe &amp; obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp; with ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlenes to be alured to vertue &amp; knowledge: To be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for his good endeauors, &amp; praiſed for his wel doing, that hee may loue learning, take delight in
<pb facs="tcp:21403:14"/>vnderſtanding and pleaſure in pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and witty diſcourſes, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto him in pure ſpeech with perfect pronuntiation.</p>
            <p>His diſcreet Schoolemaſter is to conſider his Nature, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and to frame his inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and precepts thereunto, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the child his capacitie: not to daunt his Spirite, or dull his witte: for in the recreation of his minde and memory, Muſicke and honeſt ſports are to bee vſed: And for the health of his body, moderate exerciſes are to be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed.</p>
            <p>Honeſt, ciuill and carefull men are to attend vpon him, who will giue him no bad example, but encourage him to proceed in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and learning. Wicked flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers in any caſe are to be debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from him; who to dehort him
<pb facs="tcp:21403:14"/>from humility, and the pathe of vertue, and learning, will tell him that his Schoole-maſter is his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, that he is diſcended of high Nobility, and ſhall haue liuing and landes in plentifull aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. Why ſhould hee lone the booke, why ſhould he liſten to, or bee ruled by an inferiour ſeruant? hee is to commaund: why ſhould hee bee gouerned, or in any ſort debarred of his will: It is fitte for him to take his pleaſure, and to doe what hee liſte. Thus a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, or a <hi>Gnato</hi> by ſugred words, will attempt to corrupt him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Iacobs</hi> voyce, &amp; <hi>Fſaus</hi> hands, ſmooth words, and rough works. Of all tame Creatures, a flatterer is the worſt. Likewiſe other euill diſpoſed perſons are not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude themſelues into his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: ſuch as commonly will vſe
<pb facs="tcp:21403:15"/>ſwearing, curſing, ſlaundering, lying, euill ſpeaking, or bad acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in his preſence, or hearing: They alſo are not to be admitted, to conuerſe with him, who will teach him foule &amp; fooliſh ſongs, diſhoneſt actions, or to mocke &amp; deride any one: or to doe harme to others.</p>
            <p>Theſe are to bee taken heed of, and ſharpely to bee rebuked: for children by nature are more prone to vice then vertue: and are not ſo much or ſoone furthered by things well done or ſpoken, as they bee hindered, and corrupted by deedes, lewdly committed, or wordes wickedly vttered.</p>
            <p>In a Noble man his houſe, the Schoole-maſter his place is next to the Chapleines. The of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Chapleine is to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate diuine Seruice, to preach
<pb facs="tcp:21403:15"/>and to teach the true worſhippe of of God. The office of the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter is by gentle meanes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill into his Schollers, by little and little, as their capacities are able to beare, the excellent knowledge of diuine and humane things: to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them in the Liberall Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that they may daily encreaſe and fructifie therein; with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect vnderſtanding, readie and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct ſpeaking of die learned Tongues: I mean <hi>Latine</hi> &amp; <hi>Greeke.</hi> Theſe Offices are liberall, not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile, appertaining to the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Of Offices belonging to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, the Stewards is chiefe; hee weareth the Liuery and Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of his Lord and Maſter. If the Chapleine and Schoolemaſter were ſeruants, they alſo ſhould weare the Liuery &amp; Cogniſance, as the Steward, and other ſeruants
<pb facs="tcp:21403:16"/>vſually doe. I could neuer yet bee aduertiſed, what law could be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, or what reaſons could bee rendred, why the Steward, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of the Horſe, or the Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of the Rents, ſeruants to any Noble man, being a ſubiect, ſhuld perſwade themſelues, their offices &amp; places to be aboue the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters. They are conuerſant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Seruants, Horſes, Rents, as the proper obiects of their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The Schoolemaſter about the Noble Children, as the proper ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of his Office, Are ſeruants, horſes, rents, more to bee reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted then Noble Children? Or, do they thinke, the ouer-ſeeing of certaine ſeruants, the managing of horſes, the receiuing of ſome rents, to bee preferred before the gouernance and teaching of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Children the excellent
<pb facs="tcp:21403:16"/>knowledge of diuine and humane things? Herein, as it ſeemeth, they offer indignitie, not onely to the Noble Children, but alſo to the Profeſſors of Learning, and the degrees thereof, which worthily haue aduanced, and continually doe, many from meane eſtate to true Gentilitie, Nobilitie, and to the chiefeſt Dignities. Where or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is not, there is confuſion: the Sexton there will bee aboue the Clerke.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Certaine Reaſons demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> the prioritie of Place of the Schoolemaſter, before the <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to any ſubiect.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. FIrſt, becauſe of the Vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For the Schoolemaſter is not a ſeruaut. The Steward is properly a ſemant. For proofe thereof, I referre them who are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite
<pb facs="tcp:21403:17"/>poſite in opoinion, to the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; Canons Eccleſiaſticall, &amp; to the Statute law of our Realme; where they may euidently ſee Schoole-maſters diſtinguiſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruants by ſeuerall titles, and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Statutes concerning them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, Becauſe of office; for the one is to inſtruct, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh with the knowledge of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and humane things: the other to manage matters appertaining to ſeruants.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Becauſe of the obiect of the office: for the one is to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne and teach the children: the other to ouer-ſee and order the ſeruants, which are inferiour to the children.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, Becauſe of the loue of parents, deſcending naturally to their children, which induceth them as it were by the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if they doe not vnnaturally
<pb facs="tcp:21403:17"/>abandon naturall loue &amp; learning, to preferre him, who hath the edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and inſtruction of their children, before a ſeruant.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Fiftly, Becauſe of diſcretion and wiſedome that is or ought to be in Parents, being very lawfull &amp; forcible motiues to cauſe them more to grace and countenance the Maſter of their children then a ſeruant: for that redoundeth to the profite, worth, and honour of their children.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Sixtly, Becauſe of the good of the children, that they may better ſtand in due regard, awe, &amp; obedience to their Maſter, may more eſteeme &amp; honour learning, wherewith being adorned, they themſelues may be more eſteemed and honoured: and conſequently continue with augmentation the name and fame of their houſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21403:18"/>
               <p n="7">7. Seuenthly: Becauſe of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, which is a law vnwritten, and ſheweth, that the Steward weareth the Liuery and Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of his Lord and Maſter: the Chapleine and Schoole-maſter doe not; for they are not ſeruants. The Steward hath a table aſſigned to him: but it is in the Hall, tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>The Stewards Table.</hi> The Chapleine and Schoolemaſter v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually ſit eyther at their Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or at a ſide table, anciently called, <hi>The Chapleines table.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Eightly: Becauſe of the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Learning, and the degrees thereof: For it were extreme fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or rather madneſſe in Parents, to bring vp their children ſo char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geably in learning, and ſemblably in their ſonnes, to beſtow ſo many yeeres, euen the prime of their time, to disburſe ſo great expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb facs="tcp:21403:18"/>to bee ſo vigilant, and to take ſuch paines for the attayning to learning, and the degrees there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto belonging; if Promotion, Preferment, Worſhip, Honour, Grace, were not the due rewards thereof. <hi>Honos alit Artes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The diuine <hi>Plato</hi> being deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded what difference there was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ignorant man, and a learned, anſwered; As much as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a ſicke man and a ſound: For blind and proud ignorance is the ſicknes, and vertuous learning the health of the ſoule. We vſually ſay, <hi>At your ſeruice. Your ſeruant. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memember my ſcruice,</hi> to ſuch, and to ſuch a one. Thoſe are meere ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball complements: when indeede we are not their ſeruants: and wee know, and take our places, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our offices and degrees.</p>
               <p>A Schoolemaſter, who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb facs="tcp:21403:19"/>the degree of Maſter of Artes in the Vniuerſities of our Land, muſt not make his office of teaching ſeruile: for a publike oath hath beene tendred and miniſtred to him, according to this forme and tenour; <hi>(viz.) Tu tueberis gradum tuum, &amp;c. Thou ſhall defend and maintaine thy degree of Arts, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Arts alwayes, and moſt truely, haue beene called <hi>Liberall:</hi> Why ſhould any perſon bee ſo lewdly diſpoſed, as to attempt to make the Profeſſion of them ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile? In what great eſtimation <hi>Phenix</hi> was, when he was Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter to <hi>Achillis, Homer</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. And in what honourable cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite <hi>Epaminondas</hi> was, when hee was Tutor to <hi>Philip,</hi> who was after King of <hi>Macedonia, Plutarch</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. <hi>Alexander</hi> the great was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to ſay openly, that he was as much beholding to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his
<pb facs="tcp:21403:19"/>Maſter, as he was to King <hi>Philip</hi> his Father: for of his Father he tooke the occaſion to liue; of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter he receiued the reaſon &amp; way to liue well. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> King of <hi>Cicily,</hi> being baniſhed by his ſubiects, taught publikely, &amp; kept a Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Schoole in <hi>Italy:</hi> He affirmed openly, that although he were exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vniuſtly by his ſubiects, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, in deſpight of them, hee did, and would ſtill reigne: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating thereby the authoritie which he had, being a Schoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ouer his ſchollers. The <hi>Cicili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> vnderſtanding his heroicall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, repented themſelues, and eſtabliſhed him in the Kingdome againe. They who will read, and aduiſedly conſider the liues of theſe moſt Noble Emperours, <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, <hi>Iualius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, Seuerus, Tacitus, Probus, Aurelius, Traian, Adrian, Antonine
<pb facs="tcp:21403:20"/>Conſtantine the great, Theodoſius, Charles</hi> the <hi>great,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne,</hi> ſhall eaſily perceyue: theſe being trayned vp in their youth by skilfull Schoolemaiſters, more to haue flouriſhed, and to haue beene more reuowmed then other Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, by reaſon they were more excellent then the other in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: whereby the ſaying of <hi>Plato</hi> is verified, <hi>That thoſe publique weales are happy, and bleſſed, wherein eyther Phyloſophers reigne, or Kings are in Philoſophie ſtudious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of what reputation Schoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in all former ages haue beene, and how neceſſary for the benefite of publique weals, experience pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and Hyſtoriographers relate, and teſtifie</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socrates, Plato, Pythagoras, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle, Iſocrates, Plutarch, Seneca, Quintilian,</hi> and very many more,
<pb facs="tcp:21403:20"/>which might bee nominated, were all Sehoolemaſters: All of them were reuerenced, and well regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their places of teaching, and at this day are renowmed for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Their publiſhed Bookes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternize their names and fame.</p>
               <p>Our Sauiour <hi>CHRIST</hi> graceth the office of teaching. Hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe taught: the twelue Apoſtles were his Schollers. They alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his commaundement, taught. Saint <hi>Marke</hi> was Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> ſcholler, Saint <hi>Luke</hi> was ſaint <hi>Paules</hi> ſcholler.</p>
               <p>Syr <hi>Thomas Elyot</hi> that right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Knight, in his booke intituled, <hi>The Gouernour,</hi> dedicated to King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, declareth three principall cauſes, why Noble men, and Gentlemen were not ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in Learning then, as their aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours were, who thereby much
<pb facs="tcp:21403:21"/>aduanced themſelues, augmented their eſtates, profited, and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted their Countrey. Contrary-wiſe, ſome of their poſteritie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay their houſes, being not fit to bee politique <hi>Stateſmen,</hi> or wiſe Councellours, or diſcreet Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, nor ſufficiently furniſhed to execute the Lawes, or to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter Iuſtice, tempered with equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, becauſe they want learned knowledge. The firſt cauſe that he alleadgeth is the pride of many Parents, who doe not eſteeme learning as they ought to doe, nor reſpect the Teacher therof, as they ſhould do. He noteth not any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect in his dayes to bee ſo ſeduced or blinded with ignorance, or to be ſo puffed vp with pride, as to account a Schoolemaſter an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ſeruant. Euen in his time
<pb facs="tcp:21403:21"/>
                  <hi>Hadrian,</hi> the ſixth of that name, was made Pope, and <hi>Wolſey</hi> was created a Cardinall, both of them were Schoolemaſters.</p>
               <p>The ſecond cauſe he affirmeth to bee the Auarice or diuers Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who being deſirous to pinch and ſpare their purſes, are loath to giue ſufficient allowance, or bountifull ſalary to a well learned Schoolemaſter. They will not buy learned knowledge for their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, vnleſſe they may haue it cheap, &amp; at a very low rate, regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding more, like <hi>Aeſops</hi> Cocke, a graine of Barly, then a precious Iewell.</p>
               <p>The third cauſe hee auouched to bee the negligence of Parents, who doe not bring vp their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth them, as nature bindeth, &amp; birth requireth,
<pb facs="tcp:21403:22"/>and as the hopefull expectance of their Countrey craueth at their hands. There are ſome Parents in our time (I am ſorry to ſpeake it) who beſore they receiue into their ſeruice a Cooke, a Falconer, or an Horſe-rider, they haue an eſpeciall care to haue them skilfull and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in their qualities, and to haue the beſt and moſt expert they can get: But when they entertaine a Schoolmaſter, to teach their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, being the props and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing ſtayes of their houſes, the monuments of their names and fame, they are deſirous to haue a young man, who will take ſmall allowance, which they terme Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, will bee an inferiour ſeruant, will waite, and ſerue at table, will vſe verball and ieſticular comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Such a one, according to their ſiniſter ſurmizes, is fitte to
<pb facs="tcp:21403:22"/>teach. They doe not much care whether hee bee well learned, or hath taken any degree of Schoole, or is lawfully allowed to teach, or hath any good methode in teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or hath had experience and approbation in the trayning vp of children, and doth vnderſtand and ſpeake perfectly pure <hi>Engliſh, Latine</hi> and <hi>Greeke,</hi> with the right accent and true pronunciation thereof. Theſe things, which are moſt materiall and neceſſary, they leaſt regard, vſing more exact di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, in making choyſe of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants for their ſports &amp; pleaſures, then of Schoolemaſters, for the vertuous education of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: wherein they ſwerue and degenerate from their wiſe Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſters, tranſgreſſe the lawes which diſtinguiſh Schoolemaſters from ſeruants. Debaſe their children, by
<pb facs="tcp:21403:23"/>making a ſeruant their Maſter, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace as much as in them lyeth, the Office of Schoolemaſters; and that which is woorſt of all, abuſe learned knowledge, being a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar bleſſing and principall benefite which Almightie God beſtoweth vpon man, by making little recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof, and accounting it as it were a ſeruile matter. I pray God they do not therfore incurre his heauy diſpleaſure and iuſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, hee threatneth by the mouth of his holy Prophet, ſaying: <hi>Becauſe thou haſt reiected knowledge, I will reiect thee.</hi> I haue diligently obſerued, and perceiue, that their children very ſeldome proue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and ſuch Parents, for the moſt part, doe not proſper. Their eſtates by little and little do decay. <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtata</hi> publiſhed an Edict, forbidding the Profeſſors
<pb facs="tcp:21403:23"/>of learning to teach the Chriſtians children. Chriſtian Parents are deſirous to haue their children taught, yet ſome of them (I would that ſome were leſſer) repute their childrens Teacher, and Maſter to be an inferiour ſeruant, exhibiting allowance vnto him not compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. The wicked Apoſtata perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted Chriſtians and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: albeit theſe doe not ſo, yet (with their fauour bee it ſpoken) they debaſe Learning, and the Chriſtian Profeſſors thereof. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> (by generall opinion the chiefeſt Philoſopher) ſayth, <hi>That to God, to our Parents, and Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, we can neuer giue enough, or that which is equall to their deſerts.</hi> Although the Philoſopher out of his wiſdome telleth vs, that we can neuer giue enough; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in this age it is thoght by (ſom
<pb facs="tcp:21403:24"/>that to Schoolemaſters there can neuer be giuen too litle. Such ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous aſperſions are caſt vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the proud ignorant. A wiſe man hearing an vnlearned Gallant ſpeake abſurdly, and nothing to the purpoſe, ſayd; <hi>En ex aurea va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gina plumbeum educit gladium: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this braue Gallant, out of his gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſheathe draweth a leaden ſword. Diogenes</hi> ſeeing an ignorant fellow ſitting vpon a ſtone, affirmed, <hi>That one ſtone there did ſit vpon another.</hi> The more a man is with vertuous knowledge beautifyed, the more he approacheth to God; and the more hee is with ignorance blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, the more neer he reſembleth a Beaſt. The heathen men indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced therunto by the law of nature, highly regarded their Profeſſours of learning. The <hi>Indians,</hi> their <hi>Gyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſophiſts:</hi> The <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> their
<pb facs="tcp:21403:24"/>
                  <hi>Semnothei:</hi> The <hi>Perſians,</hi> their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi:</hi> The <hi>Gaules,</hi> now called the <hi>French,</hi> their <hi>Druydes:</hi> The <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> their <hi>Philoſophers. Philip,</hi> King of the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> intending to conquere and ſubdue the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> not long after he had proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and made war againſt them, ſent Embaſſadours with an offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of peace, vpon condition they would put from them <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> and other learned men. <hi>Demoſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> a moſt famous Orator, ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the ſtratageme, in an eloquent Oration, wherein hee diſſwaded the people from imbracing ſuch a Peace, told them this tale: On a time there was great warre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Wolues &amp; the Sheepe; at length the Wolues, politikely and fraudulently, promiſed the Shepheards and the Sheepe to ioyne in firme friendſhippe with
<pb facs="tcp:21403:25"/>them, ſo that they would put their Dogges from them. The credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Shepheards &amp; ſimple ſheepe yeelded thereunto. As ſoone as the Dogges were gone, which protected them, the Wolues aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted the ſheepe, and deuoured them. Euen ſo, ſayd the Oratour, (my deare <hi>Athenians</hi>) the <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> if you condiſcend vnto them, will make hauocke of you preſently after the departure of the Learned men, which inſtruct and direct you.</p>
               <p>Our life, as ſacred Scripture ſheweth, is here a warfarre; wee wage warre againſt the World, the Fleſh, and the Deuill. Theſe three mortall enemies tempt and ſollicite the vnlearned, pretending to linke themſelues in league and loue with them: ſo that they would diſgrace, put or pull downe their
<pb facs="tcp:21403:25"/>Schoolemaſters, which are indeed the firſt inſtrumentall cauſes and ordinary meanes ordayned by God to furniſh and fortify them with diuine and humane know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. If theſe ſubtile aduerſaries could compaſſe effectually their plotte and proiect heerein, they would, no doubt, deale with the vnlearned, hauing none of reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or account to teach them, as the rauenous Wolues did with the ſilly ſheep, hauing none to defend them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gerſon,</hi> a famous Doctor, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſhed and gaue ouer the office of the Chauncellourſhip of <hi>Paris,</hi> being a place of high credite, and for the good of the weak publike, became an inſtructor or teacher of children. <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> that right noble, wiſe, &amp; Chriſtian Emperor, when his ſonne <hi>Arcadius</hi> was ſixe
<pb facs="tcp:21403:26"/>yeers of age, aduauncing him to the Empire, and taking an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care, to haue him furniſhed with vertue and leaming, requiſite for imperiall rule and dignitie, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed moſt exact diligence in the ſearching out, and prouiding of <hi>Arſenius,</hi> a graue, honeſt, and well learned Schoole-maſter for him. At the time he deliuered his ſonne to be taught, and did commit the charge of him to <hi>Arſenius,</hi> he ſpake in this manner: <hi>Poſtbac tu magis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eius quam ego,</hi> hereafter you are (being his Schoole-maſter) rather a father vnto him, then I. This wiſe and diſcreet Emperour, not long after co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming into the ſchoole and finding <hi>Areadius</hi> his ſonne ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and <hi>Arſenius</hi> ſtanding and reading vnto him, blamed them both, telling the one, that hee did not performe the office
<pb facs="tcp:21403:26"/>of a Maſter, and the other that hee did not ſhewe the dutie of a Scholler, and cauſed <hi>Arſeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> to ſit downe and reade, and <hi>Arcadius</hi> to ſtand vp bare-headed to giue attentiue eare to his lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: Adding theſe wordes, that then his ſonne would bee fitte for the Empire, when by humilitie &amp; obedience, hee had attained vnto ſufficient knowledge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicholas Frigantius</hi> in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Prouinces, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and manners of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſubiect to that puiſſant Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch the King of <hi>China,</hi> among other diſcourſes declared), what reuerend, dutifull, and gratefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, the inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries beare to their Schoolmaſters. For albeit (ſaith he) they haue been their ſchollers but for a ſhort ſpace, notwithſtanding, <hi>per vitam
<pb facs="tcp:21403:27"/>deinceps vniuerſam eos magiſtros ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellant, &amp; pro magiſtris colunt.</hi> In all their life time after they call them maſters, and doe reuerence them as their maſters. There is a contagious diſeaſe wherewith horſes are infected, called the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions:</hi> I feare leſt the name thereof exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to reaſonable creatures, inſomuch that ſome of them alſo, may truly be ſaid to be affected to, or infected with the faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. There is a faſhion lately ſtart vp, to haue a <hi>French-man</hi> to teach: If he ſpeak broken, and not pure and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Engliſh, with the right ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent diſtinctly pronounced, and truely write it, there is danger leſt hee hurt the Childrens eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, being farre more neceſſary for them, then the French and ſo pul downe with one hand, more then hee can build with the other. I haue had conference with diuers
<pb facs="tcp:21403:27"/>
                  <hi>French men,</hi> whom I like, &amp; loue; I haue not heard any one of them to ſpeake, and pronounce engliſh, as perfectly as an <hi>Engliſh-ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> doth.</p>
               <p>They in whom intellectuall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ouerſwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth ſenſuall appetite, do well diſcerne and perceiue, that a <hi>French-man</hi> is not able ſo much to profite, nor is ſo fitte to teach children in England, to reade, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnderſtand, ſpeake, and write per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect engliſh, latine, and greeke, as an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> is, albeit hee bee as skilfull in the latine, &amp; the greeke, as the <hi>Engliſh-man:</hi> &amp; the reaſon is, becauſe he is to make the children to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the learned tongues, by a la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage which they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues vnderſtand already: as in the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the latine, if he keepe due methode, he is to giue to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry latine worde, the true proper &amp; ſignificant Engliſhe thereof; to declare the variety of wordes
<pb facs="tcp:21403:28"/>and ſentences, which are proper, which are figuratiue: To deliuer the peculiar phraſes of euery Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: To cauſe them to obſerue <hi>Orthography:</hi> to tranſlate <hi>Engliſh</hi> into <hi>Latine; Latine</hi> into <hi>Greeke;</hi> and againe, <hi>Greeke</hi> into <hi>Latine; Latine</hi> into <hi>Engliſh.</hi> The <hi>Frenchman</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being not ſo perfect in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> as the <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> fayleth in that Language, which directeth the children to the knowledge of the other: and conſequently, is neither ſo fit to teach, nor ſo well able to profite them.</p>
               <p>Now it remaineth that I briefly refute an errour of ſome of our Countreymen, who ſtiffely hold, that the <hi>French</hi> tongue is better then the <hi>Latine:</hi> That Noblemen, Gentlemen, and Ladies, ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to learne it then the <hi>Latine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is a moſt abſurd <hi>Paradox,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21403:28"/>ſeeing that the <hi>Latine,</hi> being the Carholike, or vniuerſall Language of Chriſtians, who are learned, is commonly taught, both priuately in houſes, &amp; publikely in Schooles and Vniuerſities, throughout all Nations in Chriſtendom. A good thing, the more generall it is, the better it is. There are but three learned Tongues, the <hi>Latine, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Hebrew.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> was neuer reckoned to be any. It is peculiar to that particular Countrey, as <hi>Engliſh</hi> is to <hi>England, Iriſh</hi> to <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> ſo <hi>French</hi> to <hi>France.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> themſelues, eſpecially the Nobilitie &amp; Gentry, disburſe large expences for the trayning vp of their children in the ſtudie of the <hi>Latine.</hi> Who hath the knowledge thereof, may trauell therewith throughout all Chriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. In this tongue all learned
<pb facs="tcp:21403:29"/>Bookes, for the moſt part, are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, wherein the conferences, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, and exerciſes of the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned are performed, which promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to the degrees of Schoole, whereby Worſhipfull, Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and gracious preferments are obtayned: and is of that ſacred e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimate by the lawes of our Land, that the very reading thereof ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth many Malefactors from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely death. I doe not diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the <hi>French,</hi> but for the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes before mentioned, I prefer the <hi>Latine</hi> before it by many degrees.</p>
               <p>There hath beene an ancient and laudable cuſtome ſtill obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the wiſer and better ſort, that after their ſonnes can vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the <hi>Latine</hi> perfectly, and ſpeake it readily, to ſend them to trauell into <hi>France, Germany, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> to the intent that they
<pb facs="tcp:21403:29"/>may there learne their Languages, which they ſhal ſooner, with more facilitie and iudgement accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh and attaine vnto, hauing the <hi>Latine</hi> Tongue before: becauſe the <hi>Italian French,</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row very many words of the ſayd <hi>Latine,</hi> albeit they doe clippe, choppe, and change diuers letters and ſillables therein. VVhere they trauell, they may ſee the people, conuerſe and conferre with the better ſort, perceiue their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, diſpoſitions, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, know their orders, lawes, and cuſtomes, behold the ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Cities, the flouriſhing Academies, the courſes of the Riuers, the Caſtles, Fortreſſes, and Hauens, the fruitfulneſſe and barrenneſſe of the Soile: And ſo further, &amp; furniſh themſelues, not only with the Languages, but alſo
<pb facs="tcp:21403:30"/>with the Geographical knowledge of thoſe countries. If the gainſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers cannot produce any law, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge ſufficient authoritie to the contrary of that which is here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, I hope they will yeeld, and not ſhutte their eyes againſt the cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere light of truth, as it euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeareth. And I truſt, they will not perſeuere obſtinately in errours, remaining therein not illuminated by God, to tally eclipſed, and ſilenced.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:21403:30"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
